Register of the Howard R. Cottam Papers 1935-1980
Hoover Institution Archives
Howard Rex Cottam papers
1935-1980
84028
Hoover Institution Archives
18 manuscript boxes, 2 envelopes (7.5 linear feet)
Speeches and writings, correspondence, memoranda, clippings, and photographs, relating to agriculture in the United States; American trade and foreign relations with Brazil and Kuwait; and food aid, agricultural development, and foreign investment in developing countries.
Cottam, Howard Rex, 1910-1984.
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1984.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
1910, July 27 Born, St. George, Utah
1932 A.B., Brigham Young University
1934, Aug. 30 Married Katherine Stokes
1938 Ph.B., University of Wisconsin
1941 Ph.D., University of Wisconsin
1942-44 Agricultural economist, U.S. Department of Agriculture, War Food Administration, New York City
1944-46 Agricultural economist, U.S. Embassy, Paris
1946-47 Agricultural attache, U.S. Embassy, Rome
1947-50 First Secretary and Consul, U.S. Embassy, Rome
1950-52 Counselor, U.S. Embassy, Rome
1952-53 National War College
1953-55 Counselor, U.S. Embassy, The Hague
Deputy director, U.S. Operation Mission, The Netherlands
1956-60 Counselor, U.S. Embassy, Rio de Janiero
Director, U.S. Operation Mission, Brazil
1960-63 Deputy assistant secretary, Bureau of Near Eastern and South Asian Affairs, U.S. Department of State, Washington, D.C.
1963-69 U.S. Ambassador, Kuwait
1969-74 North American Representative, Food and Agriculture Organization of the United Nations
Food and Agriculture Organization of the United Nations.; United States. Dept. of State.; Agriculture.; Brazil--Foreign relations--United States.; Brazil.; Developing countries.; Diplomats--United States.; International relief.; Kuwait--Foreign relations--United States.; Kuwait.; United States--Foreign relations--Brazil.; United States--Foreign relations--Kuwait.; United States--Foreign relations.
- EARLY CAREER, 1910-1944. (Box 1)
  General note
  Correspondence, writings, and collected writings, arranged by physical form.
- FOREIGN SERVICE, 1944-1955. (Box 2)
  Correspondence, writings, speeches, memoranda, clippings, miscellany, and collected writings, arranged by office file.
- U.S. DEPARTMENT OF STATE, BUREAU OF NEAR EASTERN AND SOUTH ASIAN AFFAIRS, 1960-1963 (Box 2-4)
  Correspondence, speeches and writings, subject file, and miscellany, arranged by physical form.
- U.S. EMBASSY, RIO DE JANEIRO, 1956-1960. (Box 4)
  Correspondence, biographical file, speeches, reports, appointments, clippings, subject file, and miscellany, arranged by physical form.
- AMBASSADOR TO KUWAIT, 1963-1969. (Box 4-11)
  Correspondence, biographical file, speeches and writings, reports, subject file, and miscellany, arranged by physical form.
- FOOD AND AGRICULTURE ORGANIZATION OF THE UNITED NATIONS, 1969-1974. (Box 12-15)
  Correspondence, speeches, schedules, and subject file, arranged by physical form.
- POST-RETIREMENT, 1974-1984. (Box 15-17)
  Speeches, schedules, correspondence, subject file, arranged by physical form.
- DECLASSIFIED RECORDS, 1964-1975 (Box 18)
  Scope and Contents note
  Formerly security-classified government records. Includes some interfiled materials that are unclassified. Arranged chronologically by date of release by Hoover
- AUDIO-VISUAL FILE., 1933- circa 1980
- EARLY CAREER, 1910-1944
  - Correspondence, 1935-1944
    - General (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Unidentified, undated (Folder 2)
    - Alpha Kappa Delta, 1935 (Folder 3)
    - American Sociological Society, 1943 (Folder 4)
    - Ballif, George S., 1940 (Folder 5)
    - Blaesser, William W. and Helen, 1939-1941 (Folder 6)
    - Conklin, Gordon and Lillian, 1937-1946 (Folder 7)
    - Cottam, Katherine S., 1938-1940 (Folder 8)
    - Dollard, Charles, 1938-1939 (Folder 9)
    - Family correspondence, 1937-1943 (Folder 10)
    - Glick, Dr. and Mrs. Paul, 1940 (Folder 11)
    - Hettig, T. David and Florence, 1939-1940 (Folder 12)
    - Hill, George W. and Ruth, 1940 (Folder 13)
    - Jacobs, Rigby and Pauline, 1939 (Folder 14)
    - John, Dr. M. E., Pennsylvania State College, 1939-1943 (Folder 15)
    - Kerns, Dr. R. W., 1942 (Folder 16)
    - King, Morton, 1939 (Folder 17)
    - Kolb, Prof. J. H., 1937-1940 (Folder 18)
    - Lininger, Prof. F. F., Pennsylvania State College, 1940 (Folder 19)
    - Loomis, Dr. C. P., U.S. Department of Agriculture, 1939 (Folder 20)
    - Mangus, A. R., Ohio State University, 1939-1944 (Folder 21)
    - McCormick, Prof. T. C., 1939 (Folder 22)
    - Nelson, Dr. Lowry, 1934-1940 (Folder 23)
    - Oberdorfer, Doug, 1939 (Folder 24)
    - Perkins, Walter and Mary Lee, 1938 (Folder 25)
    - Roskelley, Dr. R. Welling, 1938 (Folder 26)
    - Ross, Prof. Edward A., 1937 (Folder 27)
    - Sandgren, Clyde and Zola, 1939-1940 (Folder 28)
    - Sorensen, Virginia, 1942 (Folder 29)
    - Stokes, Mary B., 1937-1938 (Folder 30)
    - Stokes, Paul and Edith, 1940-1941 (Folder 31)
    - Taylor, Carl C., 1938-1939 (Folder 32)
    - Useem, John and Ruth, 1939-1940 (Folder 33)
    - Viking Club (club of college friends), 1938-1940 (Folder 34)
    - Washburn, Barr and Bernice, 1939-1940 (Folder 35)
    - Whipple, Maurine, 1941 (Folder 36)
    - Wisconsin, University of, 1936-1939 (Folder 37)
    - Young, Kimball and Lillian, 1937-1941 (Folder 38)
  - Writings of Howard R. Cottam, 1940-1943
    - "Forms of Social Adjustment of Ohio Farmers," adapted from "Level of Living, Social Participation and Social Adjustment: A Study of the Standards of Living of 299 Ohio Farm Families," Ph.D. Thesis, University of Wisconsin, 1940. (Folder 39)
    - "Level of Living, Social Participation, and Adjustment of Ohio Farm People," (co-author with A. R. Mangus), Ohio Agricultural Experiment Station, Wooster, Ohio, September 1941.
    - "A Proposed Definition of Standard of Living," (co-author with A. R. Mangus), reprint from Social Forces, Vol. 21, No. 2, Pennyslvania State College and Ohio State University, December, 1942.
    - "Standard of Living: An Empirical Test of a Definition," reprint from Rural Sociology, Vol. 7, No. 4, December 1942.
    - "Housing and Attitudes Toward Housing in Rural Pennsylvania,", December 3, 1942.
    - "Housing Scales for Rural Pennsylvania," reprint from the Journal of the American Statistical Association, Vol. 38, December, 1943.
  - Collected writings of other authors, 1943 (Folder 40)
    - "The Impact of Society upon the Child,", n.d.
    - Kling, William. "Food Waste in Distribution and Use," reprint from Journal of Farm Economics, Vol. XXV, No. 4, November, 1943.
- FOREIGN SERVICE CAREER, 1944-1955
  - U.S. Embassy, Paris, 1944-1946
    - Correspondence, 1944-1948
      - Conklin, Gordon and Lillian, 1945-1947 (Box 2, Folder 1)
      - Cottam, Katherine S., 1944-1945 (Folder 2)
      - Family correspondence, 1945 (Folder 3)
      - First Security Bank of Utah, 1945-1948 (Folder 4)
      - Johnson, Dr. A. Rex, 1945 (Folder 5)
      - Miscellaneous correspondence (Folder 6)
      - Useem, John and Ruth, 1945 (Folder 7)
      - Young, Kimball and Lillian, 1945 (Folder 8)
    - Expenditures, 1945 (Folder 9)
    - Writings of Howard R. Cottam (?). "Food and Agricultural Observations From Paris to Nancy," typewritten text, July 16, 1945. (Folder 10)
  - U.S. Embassy, Rome, 1946-1952
    - Clippings, 1949-1952 (Folder 11)
    - Guest and address lists (Folder 12)
    - Memoranda, 1952 (Folder 13)
    - Miscellany (Folder 14)
    - Writings of Howard R. Cottam, 1949-1952
      - "Land Redistribution: One Aspect of Agrarian Reform in Italy," (co-author with Robert A. Brand and Victor B. Sullam), Foreign Agriculture, October, 1949. (Folder 15)
      - "Italian Agriculture, 1951," (co-author with W. E. Corfitzen, G. H. Huffman, and Eric B. Shearer), Mutual Security Agency (under the direction of the Embassy-M.S.A. Agriculture Staff), Rome, January, 1952. (Folder 16)
    - Collected writings of other authors, 1949-1952 (Folder 17)
      - "They Make Things Grow," International Labour Office, Rome, n.d.
      - "Italy-Summary of Current Economic Information," International Reference Service, January, 1949.
      - "Summary of Agrarian Reform in Italy,", March 31, 1952.
  - U.S. Embassy, The Hague, 1954-1955
    - Clipping, 1954 (Folder 18)
    - Guest lists
      - Undated (Folder 19)
      - 1954 (Folder 20)
      - 1955 (Folder 21)
    - Memorandum, 1955 (Folder 22)
    - Speeches of Howard R. Cottam, 1944-1952
      - Introduction of Jhr. Emile van Lennep, typewritten text, n.d. (Folder 23)
      - "American Attitudes toward Global Defense," Netherlands Defense Study Center, typewritten text, April 26, 1954. (Folder 24)
      - "Foreign Economic Policy of the United States," address to the Netherlands-American Chamber of Commerce, reprint from the U.S. Information Service Bulletin, September 16, 1954. (Folder 25)
      - Introduction of the Honorable P. V. Cardon, American Association, typewritten text, July 28, 1955. (Folder 26)
      - "Economic Protectionism," address to the American Association in the Hague, printed copy, November 17, 1955. (Folder 27)
- U.S. EMBASSY, BRAZIL, 1956-1960
  - Appointments and schedules, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Biographical file, 1960 (Folder 29)
  - Clippings (Folder 30)
  - Correspondence, 1957-1960 (Folder 31)
  - Guests lists
    - Undated (Folder 32)
    - 1956 (Folder 33)
    - 1957 (Folder 34)
    - 1958 (Folder 35)
    - 1959 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - 1960 (Folder 2)
  - Miscellany. Certificates, awards, directories, etc. (Folder 3)
  - Reports
    - General (Folder 4)
    - Allan, Donald M., "Management Advisory Committee, Final Report," draft and typewritten text, June 4, 1959. (Folder 5)
    - American Embassy, Rio de Janeiro (Folder 6)
    - Briggs, Lucy, "The Amazon Trip," typewritten text, August 17, 1957. (Folder 7)
    - Gorton, W. W., "The Nordeste, A Brief Summary,", n.d. (Folder 8)
    - Oberg, Kalervo, "Negotiations Relating to the Selection of Piracicabe as the Participating Agricultural College," typewritten copy, USOM/Brazil, Rio de Janeiro, May 1958. (Folder 9)
    - Office of the Agricultural Attache, "Brazil's Coffee," typewritten copy, April, 1957. (Folder 10)
    - Smith, T. Lynn, "Values Held by People in Latin America which Affect Technical Cooperation," University of Florida, n.d. (Folder 11)
    - U.S. Department of Commerce
      - "Information of Interest to Prospective Investors in Brazilian Lands," (Folder 12)
      - "Final Report of the U.S. Department of Commerce Trade Mission to Brazil,", May 12-July 1, 1960.
    - Washington, S. Walter, "A Study of the Causes of Hostility Toward the United States in Latin America: Brazil,", February 24, 1956. (Folder 13)
    - World Trade Information Service. Operations Reports (Folder 14)
      - 1955
      - 1958
      - 1959
  - Speeches by Howard R. Cottam, 1957-1960
    - Fragments and holograph notes (Folder 15)
    - "Observations on Brasilia,", n.d. (Folder 16)
    - "Observations and Impressions of Brasilia," Holograph notes, typewritten copies, clippings., August 20-21, 1957. (Folder 17)
    - Commencement Address, Escola Americana, Printed copy., June 13, 1958. (Folder 18)
    - "Point 4 in Brazil," U.S. Operations Mission in Brazil International Cooperation Administration, Department of State, Printed copy in English, printed copy in Portuguese., August 29, 1958. (Folder 19)
    - Participants of the Poultry Team, Holograph and typewritten draft, in English and Portuguese., March 14, 1959. (Folder 20)
    - Texto do Discurso Pronunciado Pelo Sr. Howard R. Cottam, Diretor do Ponto IV no Brasil, na Cerimonia Realizada no Escola Technica Federal de Industria Quimica e Textil, do Senai, Printed copy, and typewritten draft., April 17, 1959. (Folder 21)
    - Remarks for Presentation of Certificates of Achievement to Ex-Bolsistas, June 26, 1959. (Folder 22)
    - Comments at the Quitandinha Conference, November 14, 1959. (Folder 23)
    - Remarks to the Area Community Development Group Going to the U.S., September 16, 1960. (Folder 24)
    - "Diplomatecs and Diplomats," prepared for American Participants at the Convocation of Professors and Technicians, USOM/Brazil, Draft and printed copy., February 18, 1960. (Folder 25)
    - Addresses to the National Conference of Communications Media Officers Sponsored by the National Campaign for Rural Education, and by the Brazilian Naval War College, Printed copies in English and Portuguese., September 19, 1960, September 26, 1960. (Folder 26)
  - Collected speeches and writings
    - "Ambassadresses of Good Will -- or Ill,", n.d. (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Campos, Dr. Roberto de Oliveria, speech given to the Conference on Brazil, Inauguration of the Brazilian Institute of the New York University, December 1-3, 1958. (Folder 2)
    - Kiernan, Loyd J., "Autobiography of an Accident," USOM/Brazil, Report., March 4, 1960. (Folder 3)
    - Oberg, Dr. Kalervo, "Culture Shock and the Problem of Adjustment to New Cultural Environments," Women's Club of Rio de Janeiro, August 3, 1954. (Folder 4)
  - Subject file. Yacht Club, Brasilia. Certificates, and correspondence, 1960-1963. (Folder 5)
- U.S. DEPARTMENT OF STATE, BUREAU OF NEAR EASTERN AND SOUTH ASIAN AFFAIRS, 1960-1963
  - Correspondence, 1960-1963
    - General, 1961-1963 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Cabot, John Moors, 1961 (Folder 7)
    - Cameron, Turner C., Jr., 1962 (Folder 8)
    - First Security Bank of Utah, 1960 (Folder 9)
    - Gudin, Prof. Eugenio, 1960-1961 (Folder 10)
    - Hare, Raymond A., 1962 (Folder 11)
    - Hillman, Jimmye S., 1960 (Folder 12)
    - Howe, John P., 1961 (Folder 13)
    - Linder, Harold F., 1961 (Folder 14)
    - Middle East Institute, 1963 (Folder 15)
    - National War College, Alumni Association, 1961 (Folder 16)
    - Saidi, Ahmad, 1963 (Folder 17)
    - Thackara, James J., 1963 (Folder 18)
    - Thibodeaux, Dr. Ben H., 1961 (Folder 19)
    - U.S. Department of State - Foreign Service, 1963 (Folder 20)
  - Memorandum (Folder 21)
  - Miscellany (Folder 22)
  - Speeches and writings, 1961-1962
    - Unidentified, November 7, 1961 (Folder 23)
    - "Observations of the Sixteenth Selection Board C," Typewritten text, and Foreign Affairs Manual Circular, December 4, 1962. September 25, 1962 (Folder 24)
  - Subject file.
    - Cosmos Club. Correspondence, membership list, and article, 1961-1964 (Folder 25)
    - Indian Sub-continent. Visit of H. R. Cottam, Intineraries, correspondence, January 9-February 8, 1963. 1963. (Folder 26)
- AMBASSADOR TO KUWAIT, 1963-1969
  - Biographical file, 1963-1969 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Clippings
    - Undated (Folder 28)
    - 1963 (Folder 29)
    - 1964 (Folder 30)
    - 1965 (Folder 31)
    - 1966 (Folder 32)
    - 1967 (Folder 33)
    - 1968 (Folder 34)
  - Correspondence, 1963-1969
    - Correspondents include Eugene R. Black, Lyndon B. Johnson, and Dean Rusk., 1963.
      - Incoming
        - July (Folder 35)
        - August (Folder 36)
        - September (Folder 37)
        - October (Folder 38)
        - November (Folder 39)
        - December (Folder 40)
      - Outgoing (Folder 5)
        - July (Box 5, Folder 1)
        - August (Folder 2)
        - September (Folder 3)
        - October (Folder 4)
        - November (Folder 5)
        - December (Folder 6)
    - Correspondents include Hubert H. Humphrey, Daniel K. Inouye, Henry M. Jackson, and Dean Rusk., 1964.
      - Incoming
        - January (Folder 7)
        - February (Folder 8)
        - March (Folder 9)
        - April (Folder 10)
        - May (Folder 11)
        - June (Folder 12)
        - July (Folder 13)
        - August (Folder 14)
        - September (Folder 15)
        - October (Folder 16)
        - November (Folder 17)
        - December (Folder 18)
      - Outgoing
        - January (Folder 19)
        - February (Folder 20)
        - March (Folder 21)
        - April (Folder 22)
        - May (Folder 23)
        - June (Folder 24)
        - July (Folder 25)
        - August (Folder 26)
        - September (Folder 27)
        - October (Folder 28)
        - November (Folder 29)
        - December (Folder 30)
    - Correspondents include Birch Bayh, Eugene R. Black, Harlan Cleveland, and Henry M. Jackson., 1965.
      - Incoming
        - January (Box 6, Folder 1)
        - February (Folder 2)
        - March (Folder 3)
        - April (Folder 4)
        - May (Folder 5)
        - June (Folder 6)
        - July (Folder 7)
        - August (Folder 8)
        - September (Folder 9)
        - October (Folder 10)
        - November (Folder 11)
        - December (Folder 12)
      - Outgoing
        - January (Folder 13)
        - February (Folder 14)
        - March (Folder 15)
        - April (Folder 16)
        - May (Folder 17)
        - June (Folder 18)
        - July (Folder 19)
        - August (Folder 20)
        - September (Folder 21)
        - November (Folder 22)
        - December (Folder 23)
    - 1966
      - Incoming
        - January (Folder 24)
        - February (Folder 25)
        - March (Folder 26)
        - April (Folder 27)
        - May (Folder 28)
        - June (Folder 29)
        - July (Box 7, Folder 1)
        - August (Folder 2)
        - September (Folder 3)
        - October (Folder 4)
        - November (Folder 5)
        - December (Folder 6)
      - Outgoing
        - January (Folder 7)
        - February (Folder 8)
        - March (Folder 9)
        - April (Folder 10)
        - May (Folder 11)
        - June (Folder 12)
        - July (Folder 13)
        - August (Folder 14)
        - September (Folder 15)
        - October (Folder 16)
        - November (Folder 17)
        - December (Folder 18)
    - Correspondents include Lady Bird Johnson, Dean Rusk, Brigadier Gen. Ward S. Ryan, John V. Tunney., 1967.
      - Incoming
        - January (Folder 19)
        - February (Folder 20)
        - March (Folder 21)
        - April (Folder 22)
        - May (Folder 23)
        - June (Folder 24)
        - July (Folder 25)
        - August (Folder 26)
        - September (Folder 27)
        - October (Folder 28)
        - November (Folder 29)
        - December (Folder 30)
      - Outgoing
        - January (Box 8, Folder 1)
        - February (Folder 2)
        - March (Folder 3)
        - April (Folder 4)
        - May (Folder 5)
        - June (Folder 6)
        - July (Folder 7)
        - August (Folder 8)
        - September (Folder 9)
        - October (Folder 10)
        - November (Folder 11)
        - December (Folder 12)
    - Correspondents include Eugene R. Black, Gen. Wallace M. Greene, Jr., Parker T. Hart, David Kennedy, Edward R. King, William C. Ladd, David Rockefeller, George Romney, Adm. Walter L. Small, and Wendell Wyatt., 1968.
      - Incoming
        - January (Folder 13)
        - February (Folder 14)
        - March (Folder 15)
        - April (Folder 16)
        - May (Folder 17)
        - June (Folder 18)
        - July (Folder 19)
        - August (Folder 20)
        - September (Folder 21)
        - October (Folder 22)
        - November (Folder 23)
        - December (Folder 24)
      - Outgoing
        - January (Folder 25)
        - February (Folder 26)
        - March (Folder 27)
        - April (Folder 28)
        - May (Folder 29)
        - June (Folder 30)
        - July (Folder 31)
        - August (Folder 32)
        - September (Folder 33)
        - October (Folder 34)
        - November (Folder 35)
        - December (Folder 36)
    - Correspondents include George W. Ball, Harlan Cleveland, William O. Hall, Clifford M. Hardin, W. Averell Harriman, Parker T. Hart, Adm. Harry Hull, Emil Mosbacher, Jr., George Romney, and Philip D. Shea., 1969.
      - Incoming
        - January (Box 9, Folder 1)
        - February (Folder 2)
        - March (Folder 3)
        - April (Folder 4)
        - May (Folder 5)
        - June (Folder 6)
        - July (Folder 7)
        - August (Folder 8)
      - Outgoing
        - January (Folder 9)
        - February (Folder 10)
        - March (Folder 11)
        - April (Folder 12)
        - May (Folder 13)
        - June (Folder 14)
        - July (Folder 15)
  - Family and personal correspondence
    - Undated (Folder 16)
    - 1963 (Folder 17)
    - 1964 (Folder 18)
    - 1965 (Folder 19)
    - 1966 (Folder 20)
    - 1967 (Folder 21)
    - 1968 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - 1969 (Folder 2)
  - Miscellany. Cards, invitations, address and phone lists, Christmas card lists, guest lists, maps, permits, directories, postcards, visas, etc. (Folder 3)
  - Speeches and writings of Howard R. Cottam, (consisting mainly of typewritten texts and printed copies), 1963-1969
    - Undated holograph notes and fragments (Folder 4)
    - Undated and untitled typewritten texts (Folder 5)
    - KIESP Lecture, typewritten notes relating to the Foreign Service, undated (Folder 6)
    - "Kuwait and Its Neighbors," draft, undated (Folder 7)
    - "Middle East Aspirations and United States Objectives," draft, undated (Folder 8)
    - "Sovereignty in World Affairs," draft and related clipping, undated (Folder 9)
    - "Iran-American Relations," 8th Annual Dinner of the Iran-American Chamber of Commerce, Inc., New York, May 22, 1963 (Folder 10)
    - Christmas Greeting from Kuwait, December 1963 (Folder 11)
    - "United States and the State of Kuwait 1964," American Women's Club, January 27, 1964 (Folder 12)
    - "Foreign Minister at Break Fast," memoranda, January 29, 1964 (Folder 13)
    - "Toast to the Oil Industry," Annual Meeting of Petroleum Institute, February 19, 1964 (Folder 14)
    - Message of the American Ambassador to Kuwait to Americans in Kuwait, July 4, 1964 (Folder 15)
    - Opening Remarks at International School of Kuwait, November 5, 1964 (Folder 16)
    - "Kuwait: A Case Study in Modernization," draft, December 7, 1964 (Folder 17)
    - "Profile of Kuwait - - By an Admirer," probably written by H. R. Cottam, April 1965 (Folder 18)
    - "Fishing Trip Resume," draft, May 13-14, 1965 (Folder 19)
    - Remarks at the American Community Independence Day Celebration, Gazelle Club, Kuwait, Includes an introduction by Isa K. Sabbagh, July 4, 1965. (Folder 20)
    - Toast to His Excellency Shaikh Sabah Al Ahmad Al Jabir Al Sahah at a Dinner Given in His Honor by the American Ambassador, August 25, 1965 (Folder 21)
    - "Role of an Ambassador," Foreign Institute, Basic Course, handwritten draft, October 8, 1965 (Folder 22)
    - "Modernization in Kuwait," Columbia University Club of Washington, D.C., National Lawyer's Club, handwritten draft, October 30, 1965 (Folder 23)
    - "United States Policy in the Middle East, Middle East Aspirations and United States Objectives," Bloomington, Indiana, November 4, 1965 (Folder 24)
    - "Modernization and Foreign Relations," Pennsylvania State University, November 22, 1965 (Folder 25)
    - "Middle East Aspirations and United States Objectives," Pennsylvania State University, November 22, 1965 (Folder 26)
    - Notes for radio interview, February 21, 1966 (Folder 27)
    - Notes for Aminoil/Embassy speech, handwritten notes, February 25, 1966 (Folder 28)